Guide to the Montana Mining Company Records 1882-1934
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
- Financial Records, 1883-1933; Series III; 4.0 linear feet and oversize materials
  - Mill Reports, 1917 (Box-folder 22/6)
  - Mill Reports, 1924, 1928 (Box-folder 22/7)
  - Mine Work Progress Reports, 1902 (Box-folder 22/8)
  - Names and Descriptions of Lodes and Claims, 1921, 1925, 1927, undated (Box-folder 22/9)
  - Payroll Records, 1887-1922 (Box-folder 22/10)
  - Payroll Records, 1887-1922 (Box-folder 35OS/2)
  - Reports on Eva, Oyster-Criterion, and Cholla Mines, British Columbia, 1908 (Box-folder 22/11)
  - Silver Bell Mine Reports, 1904 (Box-folder 22/12)
  - Supply Lists (Box-folder 32OS/8)
  - Tax Assessments and Receipts, 1888-1919 (Box-folder 22/13)
  - Tax Assessments and Receipts, 1888-1919 (Box-folder 32OS/9)
  - Tax Assessments and Receipts, 1921-1933 (Box-folder 23/1)
  - Tax Assessments and Receipts, 1921-1933 (Box-folder 32OS/10)
  - Trial Balance Sheets, 1902-1917 (Box-folder 23/2)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1883-1889 (Box-folder 23/3)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1883-1889 (Box-folder 35OS/3)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1890-1899 (Box-folder 35OS/4)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1900-1905 (Box-folder 23/4)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1900-1905 (Box-folder 33OS/1)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1906-1907 (Box-folder 23/6)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1906-1907 (Box-folder 34OS/1)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 23/7)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1917-1929 (Box-folder 23/8)
  - Working Expenses, Assets, and Liabilities, 1917-1929 (Box-folder 34OS/2)
  - Bound Volume Order Book, November 21,1887 - February 2, 1888 (Box-folder 24/1)
  - Bound Volume Order Book, February 2 - April 19, 1888 (Box-folder 24/2)
  - Bound Volume Order Book, June 30 - September 11, 1888 (Box-folder 24/3)
  - Bound Volume Order Book, September 19 - November 20, 1889 (Box-folder 24/4)
  - Bound Volume Order Book, July 6 - October 7, 1891 (Box-folder 25/1)
  - Bound Volume Order Book, January 25 - April 4, 1894 (Box-folder 25/2)
  - Bound Volume Order Book, January 22 - May 10, 1897 (Box-folder 25/3)
  - Bound Volume Order Book Rose Densmore Mine, January 22, 1889 - April 14, 1890 (Box-folder 25/4)
  - Bound Volume Delivery Book, Montana Mining Company, December 1, 1889 - July 27, 1891 (Box-folder 26/1)
- Governance, 1886-1933; Series IV; 1.0 linear foot and microfilm
  This series contains materials related to the governance of both the Montana Mining Company and the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company. The material is primarily focused on official company correspondence, decisions, and records. The bulk of material is concentrated in the period from 1911 to 1933 and the control of the Drumlummon by the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company. The information includes reports from the Board of Directors, cable reports from the Montana Mining Company, mining reports from outside experts, mine superintendent reports, and the letters and reports of the corporate officers of the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company. Bondholder and Stockholder records and letters represent the majority of the material in the series. The divisive struggles that plagued the mine after the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company took control of the property are clearly documented here. The fight to raise money for mine improvements and to fend off bankruptcy can be traced in the letters and reports. These letters and reports contain requests for share assessments, candid evaluations of the company's financial situation, and accusations of mismanagement from various stockholder factions. The reports from the secretary of the Montana Company are generally quarterly earnings statements, although there are some monthly returns and some changes in share volume and working capital. Most of the officers' material from the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company is also related to the financial struggles of the company beginning in 1908. The bulk of these folders contain letters to stockholders asking for money, assessing shares, or reporting on the desperate financial straits of the corporation. The reports from outside mining experts candidly assess the mineral and financial opportunities available at the Drumlummon mine at two significant points in the mine's history. The first round of reports is from 1882 to 1885 and was used by the Montana Mining Company to judge the value of the property prior to their initial purchase of the mine from Thomas Cruse. The second report is from Harry Quinby criticizing the management of the mine by St. Louis Mining and Milling superintendent William Mayger in 1912. The superintendents' reports span nearly the entire life of the Drumlummon from 1885 to 1929. They provide insight into the more routine workings of the mine and the breadth of expertise required of a mine manager. These reports also provide a more intimate overview of the workings of the mines than the reports of the company officers. The series is rounded out by cable reports to the London headquarters of the Montana Mining Company from 1886 to 1901 and a number of unidentified mine reports.
  - Board of Directors, 1886-1932 (Box-folder 27/1)
  - Bondholder and Stockholder Records and Letters, 1886-1911 (Box-folder 27/2)
  - Bondholder and Stockholder Records and Letters, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 27/3)
  - Bondholder and Stockholder Records and Letters, 1912-1913 (Box-folder 34OS/3)
  - Bondholder and Stockholder Records and Letters, 1914-1915 (Box-folder 27/4)
  - Bondholder and Stockholder Records and Letters, 1916-19 (Box-folder 27/5)
  - Bondholder and Stockholder Records and Letters, 1925-1933 (Box-folder 27/6)
  - Cable Reports, 1886-1901, undated (Box-folder 27/7)
  - Engineer's Reports, 1912 (Box-folder 27/8)
  - Expert's Reports on Mine and Company, 1882-1885 (Box-folder 27/9)
  - Expert's Reports on Mine and Company, 1882 (Reel 1)
  - Expert's Reports on Mine and Company, 1907-1918 (Box-folder 28/1)
  - President - St. Louis Mining and Milling Company, 1913-1922 (Box-folder 28/2)
  - Secretary, Montana Mining Company, 1884-1908 (Box-folder 28/3)
  - Secretary, St. Louis Mining and Milling Company, 1909-1912 (Box-folder 28/4)
  - Secretary, St. Louis Mining and Milling Company, 1913 (Box-folder 28/5)
  - Secretary, St. Louis Mining and Milling Company, 1925-1933 (Box-folder 28/6)
  - Superintendents' Reports, 1885-1929 (Box-folder 28/7)
  - Vice President and Treasurer, St. Louis Mining and Milling Company, 1911-1930 (Box-folder 28/8)
  - Unidentified Reports, 1909 (Box-folder 28/9)
- Legal Documents, 1875-1931; Series V; 1.0 linear foot and oversize materials
  This series contains material relating to the legal affairs of both the Montana Mining Company and the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company. The series is arranged chronologically with materials grouped in folders according to years. The series begins with a Marysville mining claim from 1875 which is housed in an oversize box. The bulk of the remaining material relates to the apex litigation between the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company and the Montana Mining Company beginning in 1890 and continuing until the settlement of the suit in 1911. The majority of documents from the case are legal briefs but there also legal decisions, summons, injunctions, and sheriff's deeds. The papers provide insight into the bitter legal battle for control of the mining ground in question. This struggle resulted in the eventual victory of the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company and the sale of the Montana Mining Company's property at sheriff's sale in 1911. There are also briefs and other documents relating to litigation between the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company and a number of suppliers and employees. The documents in the series after 1911 relate to the struggle for control of the St. Louis Mining and Milling Company. The resulting fight to keep the Drumlummon open was waged among stock and bondholders and in court from 1911 to the closing of the mines in the 1930's. The remainder of the series is rounded out by attorney's bills, garnishment of wages, leases, settlements with injured workers, and an undated brief from the U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals.
  - Mining Claim, 1875 (Box-folder 34OS/4)
  - Documents, 1884 (Box-folder 29/1)
  - Documents, 1890-1891 (Box-folder 29/2)
  - Documents, 1893-1894 (Box-folder 29/3)
  - Documents, 1895-1896 (Box-folder 29/4)
  - Documents, 1897-1898 (Box-folder 29/5)
  - Documents, 1899-1901 (Box-folder 29/6)
  - Documents, 1902-1903 (Box-folder 29/7)
  - Documents, 1904-1905 (Box-folder 29/8)
  - Documents, 1907-1908 (Box-folder 29/9)
  - Documents, 1909-1910 (Box-folder 29/10)
  - Documents, 1911-1912 (Box-folder 29/11)
  - Documents, 1913-1914 (Box-folder 29/12)
  - Documents, 1915-1916 (Box-folder 29/13)
  - Documents, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 29/14)
  - Documents, 1921-1922 (Box-folder 29/15)
  - Documents, 1923-1924 (Box-folder 30/1)
  - Documents, 1925-1926 (Box-folder 30/2)
  - Documents, 1927-1929 (Box-folder 30/3)
  - Documents, 1930-1931 (Box-folder 30/4)
  - Documents, U.S. Court of Appeals Brief, undated (Box-folder 30/5)
  - Documents, undated (Box-folder 30/6)
- Printed Materials, 1870-1989; Series VI; 0.5 linear feet
  This small series contains a smattering of printed materials. There are newspaper clippings from Helena and Butte newspapers from 1924 to 1989. The majority of the articles pertain to attempts at re-opening the Drumlummon mine. There is a folder containing undated signs relating to safety and worker's compensation in the mine. A copy of Slater's Telegraphic Code from 1870 is included here and is useful in deciphering some of the coded telegrams sent from Marysville to the London headquarters of the Montana Mining Company. There are reports of the Montana Society of Civil Engineers from 1897. These include meeting summaries and a list of all Society members in February 1897. Finally there are printed materials with the headings of the Montana Mining Company and the Drumlummon Provident and Accident Insurance Association. These include unused envelopes, stationery, labor use reporting sheets for the mine and mills, and order forms.
  - Clippings, 1924 -1989 (Box-folder 31/1)
  - Employee Notice Signs (Box-folder 31/2)
  - Slater's Telegraphic Code Book, 1870 (Box-folder 31/3)
  - Society of Montana Civil Engineers, 1897 (Box-folder 31/4)
  - Stationery and Letterhead (Box-folder 31/5)